<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CIBIM Lab</title>
    <description>CIBIM Lab</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/cibim//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 18:24:31 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 18:24:31 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wearable monitoring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the electroencephalogram (EEG) is recorded with expensive hardware in a highly controlled lab environment. In order to enable brain monitoring in daily life situations, we built in collaboration with Stefan Debener from Oldenburg University a small, lightweight and wireless system that can be steered with Android software. This makes the concept of fully mobile EEG-based brain monitoring and real-life Brain Computer Interfaces (BCI) very realistic. Mobile EEG is needed in various contexts, e.g. for long-term neurorehabilitation programs in home environments, for assessing listening effort or monitoring correlations of auditory attention in challenging listening environments to steer hearing devices, monitoring drowsiness, improving brain fitness in the elderly, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One drawback of using traditional EEG caps in natural environments is that it attracts attention. Therefore, we focus research efforts on miniaturizing the mobile EEG device. A first prototype of a near-invisible high-quality brain monitoring device was developed in collaboration with Neuropsychology at the University of Oldenburg, CRITIAS (ETS, Montreal) and Sonomax, as shown in the figure. Such around-the-ear devices allow for continuous and reliable monitoring of brain activity and have the additional possibility to record vital signs in a convenient way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our group aims to advance machine learning and signal processing routines to extract relevant information from the brain for different real-life applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//wearable/2017/04/06/project-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cibim//wearable/2017/04/06/project-1/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Wearable</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sleep and Circadian monitoring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting a good night’s sleep is vital to cognitive functioning, protecting mental health, physical health and quality of life. Sleep is also important for recovery after diseases like stroke. And yet, daytime sleepiness is common among stroke survivors, leading in one third of the patients to a chronic problem. The science of sleep emerges as a critical clinical discipline and the goals of the recently established Sleep and Circadian Neuroscience Institute (SCNi) are to advance our understanding of how sleep and circadian rhythm disruption impacts health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sleeping disorders are currently diagnosed using polysomnography, which monitors different physiological signals overnight such as the heart rate, respiration, EEG, and eye movement.   Although polysomnography is important as diagnostic tool in sleep medicine, the high costs and low comfort cause the sleep-related disorders (e.g. obstructive sleep apnea, sleep-wake cycle disorders, …) to be under-diagnosed.  Our goal is to develop new signal and video processing routines that allow quantifying in a user-friendly and accurate way mental health and sleep anomalies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//mental%20health/2017/04/05/project-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cibim//mental%20health/2017/04/05/project-2/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Mental Health</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital technologies in Mental Health Monitoring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some description in plain text&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//mental%20health/2017/04/04/project-3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cibim//mental%20health/2017/04/04/project-3/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Mental Health</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital technologies in Neurological Disorders</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some description in plain text&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//neurological%20disorders/2017/04/03/project-4/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cibim//neurological%20disorders/2017/04/03/project-4/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Neurological Disorders</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Computational approaches for ...</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In our information era, the amount of data one has access to is tremendously increasing in quantity and variety.  Problems in computational neuroscience, neuroinformatics, pattern recognition, signal processing and machine learning give rise to massive amounts of multidimensional and multimodal data with intrinsic high dimensionality.  This data is worth nothing by itself. The true value lies in the information that is potentially contained in the data. Data has to be mined for extracting knowledge and understanding its underlying processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crucial for data mining is the format in which the data is represented.  Arrays with two or more dimensions, which we call matrices and tensors, serve as the computer representation of many types of data. Tensors provide often a natural and compact representation for such massive multidimensional data often available in long-term biomedical monitoring applications. In order to tackle big data analytics, we develop and optimise novel tools that efficiently process huge datasets. This approach to multidimensional big data is often called multiway analysis, which aims to represent the observations with a small number of variables by exploiting the underlying structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;![alt text](img/portfolio/tensors.png &quot;Tensors used in classification&quot;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ever-increasing volume of data demands algorithms that can deal with the curse of dimensionality, while the growing variety of data requires sophisticated approaches to datafusion, i.e. analysing several sources of data at once.   Also solutions for missing data (or discarding data of insufficient quality) can be designed in the tensor framework. We demonstrated in the past that the development of tensor tools is useful for very different applications in medical engineering, e.g. in neonatal monitoring, epilepsy monitoring, classification of single-trial brain responses, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//algorithms/2017/04/02/project-5/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cibim//algorithms/2017/04/02/project-5/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Algorithms</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Global health</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some description in plain text&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/cibim//global%20health/2017/04/01/project-6/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/cibim//global%20health/2017/04/01/project-6/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Global Health</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
